<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The booke o[f] merrie riddles Together with proper questions, and witty prouerbs,to make pleasant pastime. No lesse vsefull then behoouefull, for any young man or childe, to knowe whether he be quick-witted or no.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3322.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115147</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850366</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850366</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15563</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16403)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15563)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 645:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The booke o[f] merrie riddles Together with proper questions, and witty prouerbs,to make pleasant pastime. No lesse vsefull then behoouefull, for any young man or childe, to knowe whether he be quick-witted or no.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p. : woodcut ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Beale?] for Roger Iackson, and are to bee sold at his shop neere Fleet-street Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf contains a woodcut and a poem; title page A2r.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3323a on UMI microfilm reel 645.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; leaves B4 and C8 lacking; some leaves mended, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Riddles.</term>
               <term>Proverbs, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:15563:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15563:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15563:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>IS thy wit quicke?</l>
               <l>Than do not ſtick</l>
               <l>To read theſe Riddles dark:</l>
               <l>Which if thou doo,</l>
               <l>And rightly too,</l>
               <l>Thou art a wittie Spark.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15563:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BOOKE O MERRIE <hi>Riddles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with proper Queſtions, and witty Prouerbs, to make pleaſant paſtime.</p>
            <p>No leſſe vſefull then behoouefull, for any young man or childe, to knowe whether he be quicke witted or no.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop neere Fleet-ſtreet Conduit. 1617.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="riddles">
            <pb facs="tcp:15563:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15563:3"/>
            <div n="1" type="riddle">
               <head>Heere beginneth the firſt Riddle.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo legges ſate vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> legges, and had one legge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> her hand, then in came foure legges and bare away one leg, then vp ſtart two legs, and threw thrée legs at foure legs, and brought one legge againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a woman with two legs, that ſate on a ſtoole with thrée legges, and had a legge of mutton in her hand, then came a dogge which hath foure legges, and bare away the legge of mutton, then vp ſtart the woman and threw the ſtoole with thrée legges, at the dogge with foure legges, and brought the legge of mutton againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="riddle">
               <head>The 2. Riddle.</head>
               <l>He went to the wood and caught it,</l>
               <l>He ſate him downe and ſought it,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he could not find it,</l>
               <l>He brought it home with him.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:4"/>
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thorne, for a man went to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> caught a thorne in his foot, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him downe, and ſought to haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> out, and becauſe he could not finde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> muſt needs bring it home.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="riddle">
               <head>The 3. Riddle.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> worke is that, the faſter yee worke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it is ere yee haue done, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ye worke, the ſooner ye make an end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is turning of a ſpit: for if ye turne faſt, it will be long ere the meat be enough, if yee turne ſlowly, it will be the ſooner enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="riddle">
               <head>The 4. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that that ſhineth bright al day, and at night is raked vp in his owne dirt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is the fire, that burneth cleere all the day, and at night is raked vp in his aſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="riddle">
               <head>The 5. Riddle.</head>
               <l>I haue a trée of great honour,</l>
               <l>Which tree beareth both fruit and flower,</l>
               <l>Twelue branches this trée hath nake,</l>
               <l>Fifty neſts therein be make,</l>
               <l>And euery neſt hath birds ſeuen,</l>
               <l>Thanked be the King of heauen:</l>
               <l>And euerie bird hath a diuerſe name,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:4"/>
               <l>How may all this together frame?</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That tree is the yeere, the twelue branches, the twelue noneths, the fiftie two neſts, bee the fiftie two weekes, the ſeuen birds, be the ſeuen dayes in the wéeke, whereof euery one hath a diuerſe name.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="riddle">
               <head>The 6. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that, that is rough within, and red without, and briſtled like a beares ſnowt: there is neuer a Lady in this land, but will be content to take it in her hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is an Eglantine berrie, for that is rough within, and redde without, and hath briſtles on the tep.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="riddle">
               <head>The 7. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What Kings, Quéenes, and their ſeruants be they, that bee burnt once a yéere, and bee cut and torne as ſmall as fleſh to the pot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Thoſe bee the Kings and Quéenes and var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets among the cards, that be ſome burned, and ſome torne, and ſome cut.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="riddle">
               <head>The 8. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that, that hath his belly ful of mans meat, and his mouth full of dirt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:5"/>
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is an Ouen when it is full of bread, or pies, for that is mans meat, and the Ouens mouth is then cloſed with dirt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="riddle">
               <head>The 9. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that that hath a beard of fleſh, a mouth of horne, and feet like a Griffon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a Cocke, for his beard is fleſh, his bill horne, and his feet like a Griffon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="riddle">
               <head>The 10. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that, the more yelay on, the faſter it waſteth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a Whetſtone, for the more yée whet the leſſe is the whetſtone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="riddle">
               <head>The 11. Riddle.</head>
               <p>Of what facultie be they, that euerie night turne the ſkins of dead beaſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Thoſe be the religious perſons, for euery night at Mattens, they turne the leaues of their Parchment bookes, that bee made of ſhéepe ſkinnes, or calnes ſkinnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="riddle">
               <head>The 12. Riddle.</head>
               <l>Two blacke,</l>
               <l>Leapt ouer the lake,</l>
               <l>With their mouths full of mans bones.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:5"/>
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a paire of ſhooes on a mans féete, when a man leapeth ouer a lake, for they bee blacke, and they are within full of mans fleſh and bones.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="riddle">
               <head>The 13. Riddle.</head>
               <l>Three priſoners ſuch as it was,</l>
               <l>Were ſhut vp in a priſon of glaſſe,</l>
               <l>The priſon doore was made of bread,</l>
               <l>And yet they were for hunger dead.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Thoſe were thrée flies that were ſhut vp in a Glaſſe, and the mouth of it ſtopped with a péece of bread.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="riddle">
               <head>The 14. Riddle.</head>
               <l>Little boy bunting,</l>
               <l>Sate on the houſe eaſing,</l>
               <l>With a bow and a bolt,</l>
               <l>Slaieth the king and all his folke.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is death, which ſlaieth Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Dukes, Earles, Gentlemen, and euery liuing creature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="riddle">
               <head>The 15. Riddle.</head>
               <l>Yonder ſide ſea is there a bote,</l>
               <l>The kings daughter of England, there ſhée ſate:</l>
               <l>And if ye tell me her name, no man it wot,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:6"/>
               <l>What was the maids name that ſate in the bote?</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Her name is Anne, for in the fourth line it ſaith, An if ye tell be her name: but this rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle is not to bee ſéene on the booke, but it is to bee put without the booke, or elſe it ſhall ſoone be vnderſtood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="riddle">
               <head>The 16. Riddle.</head>
               <l>M. and I. made great mone,</l>
               <l>When C. vpon C. was left alone.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is Marie and Iohn made great mone, When Chriſt on a Croſſe was left alone. For Marie beginneth with M. Iohn begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with I, Chriſt beginneth with C, and Croſſe beginneth with C. Alſo this riddle may be put another way, and that is this. A thouſand and one made great mone, when a hundred on a hundred was left alone. For M, is for a thouſand, and I, is for one, and C, for a hundred, and then is M. for Mary, I. for Iohn, C. for Chriſt, and then is the riddle very defuſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="riddle">
               <head>The 17. Riddle.</head>
               <p>Who bare the beſt burthen that euer was borne, at any time ſince, or any time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:6"/>
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It was the Aſſe that bare both our Lady and her ſonne out of Egypt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="riddle">
               <head>The 18. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is the moſt profitable beaſt, and that men eat leaſt on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a Bee, for it maketh both hony and wax, and coſteth his maſter nothing the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="riddle">
               <head>The 19 Riddle.</head>
               <l>I am without it, and yet I haue it,</l>
               <l>Tell me what it is, I pray God ſaue it.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is my heart, for I am without it, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that it is within mee, for yee may not vnderſtand by the riddle that I lacke it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="riddle">
               <head>The 20. Riddle.</head>
               <l>What is that is like a mede,</l>
               <l>And is not paſt a handfull brede,</l>
               <l>And hath a voyce like a man,</l>
               <l>You will tell me this, but I wot not whan.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a little Popingay, for it is greene like a mede, and is not paſt a handfull brede, and it ſpeaketh like a man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="riddle">
               <head>The 21. Riddle.</head>
               <l>L. and V. and C. and I.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:7"/>
               <l>So height my Lady at the font ſtone.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Her name is Lucy, for in the firſt line is L. V. C. I. which is Lucy: but this riddle muſt bee put and read thus, fifty and fiue, a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and one: then is the riddle very proper, for L. ſtandeth for fifty, and V. for fiue, C. for a hundred, and I. for one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="riddle">
               <head>The 22. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that one ſeeketh for, and would not finde?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is, a hole in his ſhooe, or a peece of pilgrims ſalue on a ſeege boord, when hee commeth darklong in the night.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="riddle">
               <head>The 23. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that I wiſh for, and would not haue?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is heauen, for many a man wiſheth that hee were in heauen: and though they knew ſure that they ſhould goe thither ſtraitwaies, yet would they bee loth to die and goe thither: And this riddle may be ſoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led another way, as when a man or woman doth ſay, a vengeance and a peſtilence on her childe, or on her ſeruants, or wiſheth them dead, yet would ſhe be loth it were ſo.
<pb facs="tcp:15563:7"/>Mary percaſe if ſome woman wiſh ſuch a wiſh to her huſband, then peraduenture this riddle could not thereby be aſſoyled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="riddle">
               <head>The 24. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that as high as hall, as bitter as gall, as ſoft as ſilke, as white as milke?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a walnut, for it groweth as hie as a hall, and the ſhell is as bitter as gall, and the rinde that couereth the kernell, is as ſoft as ſilke, and the kernell is as white as milke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="riddle">
               <head>The 25. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What was hee that ſlew the fourth part of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That was Cain, when he ſlew his brother Abel, for then there were no more perſons in the world but foure, that is to ſay, Adam, Eue, Cain and Abel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="riddle">
               <head>The 26. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What three heads be they that vphold the world?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Thoſe bee, the hammer head, the plough bead, and the head that multiplieth the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="riddle">
               <head>The 27. Riddle.</head>
               <p>what man is he that getteth his liuing back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:8"/>
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a Ropemaker, for as hee maketh his Ropes, he goeth alwayes backward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="riddle">
               <head>The 28. Riddle.</head>
               <l>Fiue brethren were bred at once,</l>
               <l>Without any fleſh, bloud, or bones,</l>
               <l>Two haue beards, and two haue none,</l>
               <l>The fift hath but halfe a one.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>The fiue brethren, be <hi>5.</hi> greene barbes vnder the roſe leaues, which ſpring all at once, and two of them haue briſtles like beardes on the edges and the other two haue none, but they be plaine on the edges, and the fiſt is briſtled or bearded on the one ſide, and plain on the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="riddle">
               <head>The 29. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is he that goeth to the water, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſh his guts at home.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a pillow béere, for when it goeth to waſhing, the pillow and the feathers bee left at home.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="riddle">
               <head>The 30. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is hee that goeth to the water on his head.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a horſeſhooe naile, for the head is downeward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="riddle">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:8"/>
               <head>The 31. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that that goeth to the water, and the firſt that toucheth the water is his arſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a bucket in a well, or a payle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="riddle">
               <head>The 32. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What be they that be all day full, and empty at night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a paire of ſhooes, for all day they be full with mans féet, and at night when he goes to bed, they be empty: and it may bee aſſo yled by any other part of mans raiment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="riddle">
               <head>The 33. Riddle.</head>
               <p>Who is hee that eateth his mother in his grandams belly?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a worme in a nut, for of the kernell of the nut commeth the worme, therefore the kernell is héere taken for the mother of the worme: and of the ſhel the kernel commeth: and therefore the ſhell is héere taken for the mother of the kernell, and the grandame of the worme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="riddle">
               <head>The 34. Riddle.</head>
               <p>Who is he that runneth through the hedge, and his houſe on his backe?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:9"/>
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a ſnaile, which whereſoeuer he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he carrieth his houſe on his backe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="riddle">
               <head>The 35. Riddle.</head>
               <p>To what poore man is a mans almes worſt beſtowed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a blind man, for hee would with a good will ſée him hanged that giueth him the almes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="riddle">
               <head>The 36. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What folke be they that loue not to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Thoſe be beggers and poore folk, when men ſay, I pray God helpe you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="riddle">
               <head>The 37. Riddle.</head>
               <p>Ten mens ſtrength, and ten mens length, and tenne men cannot ſet it on end, what is that?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a great roape or cable, of ten fadome in length or more, which ten men cannot ſet on end, nor ten ſcore, nor ten thouſand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="riddle">
               <head>The 38. Riddle.</head>
               <p>I gathered apples in a garden, and ere I could get out, I payd tolc for them at three gates. At the firſt gate I paid halfe the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb facs="tcp:15563:9"/>that I had gathered, and one more, and at the next gate I paid halfe the apples that I had left, and one more, and at the third gate I paid halfe the apples that I had left, and one more, and when I came out I had but one apple left: tell mee now how many apples I gathered in all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Hee gathered in all xxii. apples, for at the firſt gate he paid a xi. that was halfe, and one more, that was xii. ſo he had left ten, then at the ſecond gate he paid fiue, that was halfe, and one more, that was ſipe, ſo had hee left foure, and at the laſt gate hee paid two, that was halfe, and one more, that was iii. and ſo he had one left.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="riddle">
               <head>The 39. Riddle.</head>
               <p>Garden waies, comfort of flowers, to hight my Lady, what hight yours?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Her name wis Aliſon, for the waies in the gardens be called Allis, and the ſunne is the comfort to all flowers, &amp; ſo put them two to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and that maketh Aliſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="riddle">
               <head>The 40 Riddle.</head>
               <l>The Deare complaines and mones,</l>
               <l>The Heron féeding in her place,</l>
               <l>This is the name of my Ladies grace.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:10"/>
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Her name is Braybrook, for when the Deare complaines, hunters ſay he brayeth, &amp; the place of a Heron is a brooke, &amp; then put them two together, and that makes Braybrooke. But this riddle was made by ſame Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for his Ladies pleaſure, and is neither proper for euery man, nor eaſie to be aſſoiled</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="riddle">
               <head>The 41. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that ſtan deth on this ſide the wood, and looketh ouer the wood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a Sow, that hath a yoke about her necke, for her féete bee on this ſide the wood, and her head is ouer the wood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="riddle">
               <head>The 42. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that goeth to the wood, and his head homeward.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is an are hanging vpon a mans backe, when he goeth to the wood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="riddle">
               <head>The 43. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that goeth to the wood, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his way on his necke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a man that goeth to the wood to fell boughes, and carrieth a ladder on his necke to get vppe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="riddle">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:10"/>
               <head>The 44. Riddle.</head>
               <p>I came to a trée where were apples, I eat no apples, I gaue away no apples, nor I left no apples behinde mee. And yet I eat, gaue away, and left behinde me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>There were thrée apples on the trée, for I eat one apple, and gaue away one apple, and left one. And then I eate no apples, for I eate but one apple, which is no apples, and thus I gaue away no apples, for I gaue but one, and thus I left no apples, for I left but one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="riddle">
               <head>The 45. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that as ſmall as a nit, and ſerues the king at euery bit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is ſalt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="riddle">
               <head>The 46. Riddle.</head>
               <l>There is a water that I muſt paſſe,</l>
               <l>The broadeſt water that euer was,</l>
               <l>And yet of all waters that euer I ſée,</l>
               <l>To paſſe it ouer is leaſt ieopardy.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is the dew, for that lieth ouer all the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="riddle">
               <head>The 47. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that, the more it is, the leſſe men
<pb facs="tcp:15563:11"/>feare it, and the leſſe it is, the more men dread it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a bridge, for if it be little, we are afraid to go ouer it for falling, and if it be bigge, we feare no more to goe ouer it, then on the ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="riddle">
               <head>The 48 Riddle.</head>
               <p>I bought a brace of hounds for my Lordes grace, and when I departed from his place, I neither left them there, nor tooke them with mee, this maruellous thing how may it bee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>I left one of the greyhounds there, and took the other with mee, ſo then I neither left them there, nor tooke them with me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="riddle">
               <head>The 49. Riddle.</head>
               <p>Here I haue it, and yonder I ſée it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is my breath in a myſtie morning, for héere I haue it at my mouth, and yonder I ſée it a yard from me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="riddle">
               <head>The 50. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that is higher then a hall, or a houſe and it ſéemes much leſſer then a mouſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a ſtarre in the ſkie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="riddle">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:11"/>
               <head>The 51. Riddle.</head>
               <l>My Louers will,</l>
               <l>I am content for to fulfill,</l>
               <l>Within this rime his name is framed,</l>
               <l>Tell me then how he is named.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>His name is William, for in the firſt line is will, and in the beginning of the ſecond line is, I am, and then put them both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that maketh William.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="riddle">
               <head>The 52. Riddle.</head>
               <l>What is that, that is as white as ſnow,</l>
               <l>And yet as blacke as any crow,</l>
               <l>And more pliant then a wand,</l>
               <l>And is tied in a ſilken band,</l>
               <l>And euery day a Princes péere,</l>
               <l>Looketh vpon it with a ſad chéere.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a booke tied within a ſilken lace, for the paper of it is as white as ſnow, and the inke is as blacke as a crow, and the leaues bee more pliant then a wand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="riddle">
               <head>The 53. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What ſpace is it from the higheſt of the ſea to the bottom.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is but a ſtones caſt, for bee the ſea neuer ſo déepe, a ſtone if it be caſt in, will reach to the bottome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="riddle">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:12"/>
               <head>The 54. Riddle.</head>
               <p>How many calues tailes will reach to the ſkie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>One if it be long enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="riddle">
               <head>The 55. Riddle.</head>
               <l>Mary an Chriſt loued very well,</l>
               <l>My Ladies name héere I do tell,</l>
               <l>Yet is her name neither Chriſt nor mary,</l>
               <l>Tell me her name then, and doe not tarry.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Her name is Maryan, for in the beginning it is ſaid, Mary an Chriſt, but this riddle is to be put without the booke, and not be read, or elſe it will ſoone be perreiued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="riddle">
               <head>The 56. Riddle.</head>
               <l>What is that as white as milke,</l>
               <l>As ſoft as ſilke,</l>
               <l>As blacke as a coale,</l>
               <l>And hoppeth in the ſtréet like a ſtéed fole.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a Pie, that hoppeth in the ſtreet, for part of his feathers bee white, and part bee blacke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="riddle">
               <head>The 57. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that goeth about the wood, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:12"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15563:13"/>will not lie in a great cheſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a long Speare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="riddle">
               <head>The 65. Riddle.</head>
               <l>What is that as round as a ball,</l>
               <l>Longer then Pauls ſtéeple, weather-cocke and all.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a round bottome of thréed, which when it is vndone, it is much longer then Pauls ſtéeple.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="riddle">
               <head>The 66. Riddle.</head>
               <p>Downe in the medow haue I two ſwine, the more meat I giue them, the lowder they cry, the leſſe meat I giue them the ſtiller they be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Theſe bee two milſtones, which the more they grinde, the more noiſe they make, and they be called ſwins heere, becauſe ſwine bée fed with corne, and ſo be they.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="riddle">
               <head>The 67. Riddle.</head>
               <p>What is that, that goeth through the wood, and toucheth neuer a twig.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is the blaſt of a horne, or the cry of a beaſt, or ſuch other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="riddle">
               <head>The 68. Riddle.</head>
               <l>What is that, that hath flue legges on
<pb facs="tcp:15563:14"/>one ſide, and three on the other.</l>
               <l>Thrée heads and ſix eares, and two things like my mother.</l>
               <l>And yet ſuch another thing as hath my brother.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a man and a woman vpon a mares backe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="riddle">
               <head>The 69. Riddle.</head>
               <l>Beyond the ſea there is an oake,</l>
               <l>And in that oake there is a neſt,</l>
               <l>And in that neſt there is an egge,</l>
               <l>And in that egge there is a yolke,</l>
               <l>That calleth together Chriſtian folke.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a clapper in a bell, within a ſtéeple, for the Church is taken for the oake, the ſtéeple is taken for the neſt, the bell is taken for the egge, and the clapper is taken for the yolke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="riddle">
               <head>The 70. Riddle.</head>
               <l>Downe in a dale there ſits and ſtands,</l>
               <l>Eight legges and two hands,</l>
               <l>Liuers and Lights, and liues thrée,</l>
               <l>I count him wiſe that tels this to me.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is a man riding on horſebacke, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a hauke ſitting on his hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="riddle">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:14"/>
               <head>The 71. Riddle.</head>
               <l>Walking abroad to take the aire,</l>
               <l>I met two Ladies bright and faire,</l>
               <l>Two pretty boyes by the hands they led,</l>
               <l>And thus vnto them both I ſaid:</l>
               <l>O ye faire Ladies I pray you tell me,</l>
               <l>By nature and kind whoſe children theſe be.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Their anſwere.</head>
               <l>Gentleman, if yee will the truth knowe plaine,</l>
               <l>The ſonnes of our ſonnes they be certaine:</l>
               <l>Brothers to our huſbands they be ywis,</l>
               <l>And truly each of them to the other vncle is.</l>
               <l>Begotten and borne in wedlocke they be,</l>
               <l>And we are their mothers we tell you truly.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Theſe two Gentlewomen had two ſonnes, the one Thomas, and the other William: Thomas married Williams mother, and William married Thomas his mother, and either of them had a ſonne by their wiues, which ſonnes muſt néedes bee the ſonnes of their ſonnes, brothers to their huſbands, the one vncle to the other, and they their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mothers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="riddle">
               <head>The 72. Riddle.</head>
               <p>Ouer a water I muſt paſſe, and I muſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:15563:15"/>ouer a lambe, a woolfe, and a bottle of hay, if I carry any more then one at once, my boate will ſinke: if I carry ouer the bottle of hay firſt, and leaue the lambe and the woolfe together, the wolfe will carry my lambe away, if I carry ouer the woolfe firſt, the lambe will eate my bottle of hay. Now would I know how I ſhould carry them ouer, ſo that I leaue not the lambe with the woolfe, nor the bottle of hay with the lambe on neither ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Firſt carry ouer the lambe, and then come againe and fetch the woolfe, and bring the lambe back again on the other ſide, and then take the bottle of hay and carry it, and then fetch ouer the lambe, and ſo the queſtion is aſſoyled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="riddle">
               <head>The 73. Riddle.</head>
               <l>There were two fathers a hunting went,</l>
               <l>And their two ſonues for the ſame intent.</l>
               <l>They caught conies in all but thrée:</l>
               <l>And euery one had one, how may that be?</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>One of the ſonnes, had a ſonne, thus hée is father, and ſtandeth both for the father and the ſonne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="riddle">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:15"/>
               <head>The 74. Riddle.</head>
               <p>I conſume my mother that bare me, I eate my nurſe that fedde mee, then I die leauing them all blind that ſaw me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Meant of the flame of a candle, which when it hath conſumed both wax &amp; wéek goeth out, leauing them in the darke which ſaw by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="riddle">
               <head>The 75. Riddle.</head>
               <p>As long as I liue, I eate, but when I drinke I die.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is the fire, which continueth ſo long as it hath matter to burne vpon, except it be quenched with water, which may be termed the death of that nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="riddle">
               <head>The 76. Riddle.</head>
               <l>Ten thouſand children beautifull of this my body bred:</l>
               <l>Both ſonnes and daughters finely deckt, I liue and they are dead:</l>
               <l>My ſonnes were put to extreame death. by ſuch as loued them well:</l>
               <l>My daughters died in extreame age, but where I cannot tell.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>That is a trée, which ſignifieth the mother, the fruite the ſonnes, and the leaues the daughters. <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:16"/>
               <head>¶ John Gooſe.</head>
               <l>LOng time ſince, when men eat butterd peaſon with a ſpoone,</l>
               <l>I had a man vnto my father, borne vnder the moone.</l>
               <l>His name was Tom Gooſe, this is true indeede,</l>
               <l>When he could liue no longer he fell ſicke and dyed.</l>
               <l>And within foure dayes after, when he was layd in graue,</l>
               <l>My mother would needes another husband haue.</l>
               <l>The more husbands the better lucke, ſome wiues do ſay the ſame,</l>
               <l>And then married ſhe one, Dick Duck was by his name.</l>
               <l>A widdoer he was, and had a daughter called Ione,</l>
               <l>She was a merry one, and a minion minſer alone:</l>
               <l>She was my ſiſter and I was her brother,</l>
               <l>By law it was ſo, it could be none other.</l>
               <l>And my mother did loue him as the turtle Doue.</l>
               <l>Yet at length my father died for loue.</l>
               <l>Then ſaid my mother, though I haue two husbands wed,</l>
               <l>I muſt liue dy the quicke (quoth ſhe) and not by the dead.</l>
               <l>Yet was ſhe tough and toothleſſe, ſhort tale to make,</l>
               <l>And married the third husband, called Iohn Drake.</l>
               <l>He loued her right well, and had his owne wiſhing,</l>
               <l>For within ten dayes he killed her with kiſſing.</l>
               <l>Then would he haue a yong woman to lengthen his life,</l>
               <l>And fell in with my ſiſter Ione, and tooke her to wife.</l>
               <l>After that I could not chuſe, though before I was her brother,</l>
               <l>But iuſtly as became me, I called her mother.</l>
               <l>At length he was ſealous, and ſhe perceiud his blindneſſe,</l>
               <l>Where vpon within a few dayes ſhe killed him with kindneſſe</l>
               <l>After he was dead, then did my mother Duck,</l>
               <l>Take me to her husband, me thought I had ſtrange luck.</l>
               <l>Becauſe firſt ſhe was my ſiſter Ione, and I, Iohn her brother,</l>
               <l>And after Iohn her ſonne, and ſhe Ione my mother;</l>
               <l>Now am I Iohn her husband, and ſhe Ione my wife,</l>
               <l>We Iohn Gooſe and Ione Duck, together muſt lead our life,</l>
               <l>¶ Now if you haue well marked,</l>
               <l>Vnto you I haue tolde;</l>
               <l>How this demand is true,</l>
               <l>Therefore you may be bold.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="questions">
            <pb facs="tcp:15563:16"/>
            <head>Proper Queſtions.</head>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <head>The firſt Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Bought thrée penny-worth of Egs lately,</l>
               <l>and for euery penny had like many:</l>
               <l>And after gaue them in almes a none</l>
               <l>vnto thrée Beggars euery each one,</l>
               <l>Some to the Beggar that aſked my firſt,</l>
               <l>the ſecond had twice ſo many iuſt:</l>
               <l>The third Beggar that there I found,</l>
               <l>had twice as many as the ſecond.</l>
               <l>Now anſwere me to this queſtion ſhortly,</l>
               <l>how many Egges had I for a penny?</l>
               <l>And how many Egges after the rate,</l>
               <l>that euery Beggar had for his part?</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>I bought ſeuen Egges for euery penny, &amp; the firſt Beggar had thrée Egges, the ſecond ſix Egs, &amp; the third beggar had twelue Egs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>The ſecond Queſtion.</head>
               <l>Two men that had in their purſes mony,</l>
               <l>the one to the other thus can ſay:</l>
               <l>Put one of thy pence of thy purſe in mine,</l>
               <l>then is in my purſe as much as in thine,</l>
               <l>Nay ſaid the other, I pray thee do thus,
<pb facs="tcp:15563:17"/>put one of thy pence into my purſe,</l>
               <l>Then haue I double as much as thou:</l>
               <l>What was in both their purſes ſay ye?</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>The one of them had fiue pence in his purſe &amp; the other had ſeuen pence in his purſe, and ſo the queſtion is aſſoyled. But if yee make the queſtion, take alwayes two pence, then the numbers muſt be ten, &amp; xiiii. of iii d. xv. &amp; one and twentie, and ſo alway procéed forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <head>The third Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> Fiſher an hundred of herrings did buy,</l>
               <l>after the rate of two for a penny:</l>
               <l>And bought an hundred in another place,</l>
               <l>three for a penny neither more nor leſſe:</l>
               <l>He put them together, and ſold anone,</l>
               <l>ſtill fiue for two pence till all were gone:</l>
               <l>Now in that bargaine I thinke that he,</l>
               <l>Eyther woon or loſt, How ſay you:</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Account euer ſixeſcore to the hundred, and reckon then, and ye ſhall finde that hee hath loſt thereby, euen foure pence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <head>The fourth Queſtion.</head>
               <l>ANother queſtion I would faine define,</l>
               <l>I wedded thy mother, &amp; thou weddedſt mine:</l>
               <l>By my wife I had a ſon ſoone after,</l>
               <l>&amp; thou vpon thy wife begatteſt a daughter.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:17"/>
               <l>This queſtion now tame would I know of thee</l>
               <l>What kin together theſe Children be.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>The Sonne was Vncle to the Daughter, becauſe that her brother was his Father: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, the Daughter was Aunt to the Sonne, becauſe her brother was his Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="question">
               <head>The fifth Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Knew a maide that once did pray,</l>
               <l>a man to lend her ſome money,</l>
               <l>Which ſwore by God, and by Saint Iohn,</l>
               <l>that to that maide he would lend none:</l>
               <l>Yet for all that, ere that he went thence,</l>
               <l>he ſaued his oth, &amp; lent her twelue pence.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>This man lay with the maide firſt, and ſo ſhe loſt her maiden-head: and afterwards he lent her twelue pence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="question">
               <head>The ſixth Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> Batcheler came a mans wife vntill,</l>
               <l>praying her his carnall luſt to fulfill:</l>
               <l>She ſware a great oath as touching that ſin.</l>
               <l>She would neuer offend with him therein.</l>
               <l>She kept her oath ſo vndefilde,</l>
               <l>that ſoone after he got her with childe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>The wiues huſband dyed firſt, and after that, the Batcheler married her lawfully,
<pb facs="tcp:15563:18"/>and with her then he had carnall copulation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="question">
               <head>The ſeuenth Queſtion:</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Knew a man which in his life,</l>
               <l>begat a childe vpon his owne wife,</l>
               <l>And when it was born, his heart was done,</l>
               <l>he looked vpon it, it was not his Sonne:</l>
               <l>Of this now tell me the true ſolution.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>The child that he begot vpon his wife was a daughter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="question">
               <head>The eight Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> Man would haue ſlaine his ſon haſtily,</l>
               <l>But one counſelled him the contrary:</l>
               <l>To ſlay thy ſonne it is well done,</l>
               <l>to dread and feare nothing:</l>
               <l>For ſuch a deed thou ſhalt haue meede</l>
               <l>of Chriſt our heauenly King.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="question">
               <head>The ninth Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> Payre of Gloues a man once bought,</l>
               <l>and them to thrée ſiſters brought,</l>
               <l>And ſaid, Caſt lots, for ſome of you thrée,</l>
               <l>ſhall weare theſe Gloues for loue of me.</l>
               <l>How might his ſaying be verified there,</l>
               <l>Yet none of them all did them weare?</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>The one of the Siſters ware the one gloue, and one of the other Siſters ware the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:18"/>
               <head>The tenth Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> Soldier that to black-heath field went,</l>
               <l>praied an Aſtronomer of his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</l>
               <l>Which wrote theſe word to him plainely,</l>
               <l>thou ſhalt goe thither well and ſafely:</l>
               <l>And from thence come whom aliue againe,</l>
               <l>neuer at that field ſhalt thou be ſlaine.</l>
               <l>The ſouldier was ſlaine there at that field,</l>
               <l>And yet the Aſtronomer his promiſe held.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>The poynting of the words, is the ſolution, as thus: Thou ſhalt go thither wel and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and from thence come home againe a-liue neuer: at that field ſhalt thou be ſlaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="question">
               <head>The eleuenth Queſtion</head>
               <l>IN Eſſex I know a place right well,</l>
               <l>where men buy Oyſters by the Buſhell:</l>
               <l>For euery Buſhell foure pence they pay,</l>
               <l>and yet for all that, the buyers may</l>
               <l>For two pence a Buſhell ſell them againe,</l>
               <l>all by one meaſure, and yet haue good gain.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>They buy theſe Oyſters when they be very ſmall, and kéepe them in créekes of the ſalt water a yeere or two, till they be great, and then one Buſhell will make ſire Buſhels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:19"/>
               <head>The twelfth Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Know a childe borne by my mother,</l>
               <l>Naturally borne as other children be:</l>
               <l>That is neither my ſiſter, nor my brother:</l>
               <l>anſwere me ſhortly what is he?</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>It is the perſon that ſpeaketh the word: for he is neither brother nor ſiſter to himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="question">
               <head>The thirteenth Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> Veſſell of wine here ſtandeth me by,</l>
               <l>of eight gallons iuſt full by the eye:</l>
               <l>An other of fiue gallons, an other of three:</l>
               <l>but thoſe twaine both empty be,</l>
               <l>Mete by three gallons of this wine truly,</l>
               <l>and thereto none other veſſell to occupy.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>Firſt fill the fiue gallon veſſel full, &amp; then with that fill the thrée gallon veſſell full then, and there remaineth in the fifth gallon veſſel two gallons: then put the thrée gallons that bee in the thrée gallon veſſell, into the eight gallon veſſell, into the fiue gallon veſſell, and then fill vp the <hi>3.</hi> gallon veſſell, with the fiue gallon veſſell, and it will receiue but one gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon thereof, becauſe there was in the thrée gallon veſſell before, but two gallons, and ſo there will remaine in the fiue gallon veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, iuſt foure gallons, and then you haue
<pb facs="tcp:15563:19"/>your purpoſe: that is to ſay, foure gallons mete truely by thoſe thrée meaſures onely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="question">
               <head>The fourteenth Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> Fiſh was late taken others among,</l>
               <l>which had a head of thrée foot long:</l>
               <l>And the taile was as long truely,</l>
               <l>as the head and halfe the body:</l>
               <l>And yet was the body without faile,</l>
               <l>as long as the head and the taile.</l>
               <l>This queſtion heere I pray thée tell,</l>
               <l>How long was the Fiſh heere euery deale.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>The taile of the Fiſh was nine foot long, and the body, was twelue foot long: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the head was thrée foot long, therefore the length of the whole Fiſh was fourtéene foot long, and ſo the queſtion is aſſoyled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="question">
               <head>The fifteenth Queſtion.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> Widdow with her horſe and maide at Douer,</l>
               <l>Prayd a Shipman into Fraunce to bring them ouer:</l>
               <l>He ſwore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neither widow, horſe, nor maide,</l>
               <l>Should into Francr for him be conuaide.</l>
               <l>How might his oth there ſaued be,</l>
               <l>Yet hee brought them into Fraunce in his</l>
               <l>Ship all thrée.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="solution">
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:20"/>
               <head>Solution.</head>
               <p>The widow was marryed, the mayde loſt her mayden-head, and the horſe was gelded: and then the Syip man carried them all ouer together in his Ship, and ſo ſaued his oath which he had taken before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="question">
               <head>The ſixteenth Queſtion.</head>
               <l>ONe ſaide, God ſpéed dame with the</l>
               <l>Geeſe twentie,</l>
               <l>Nay ſix, ſaid ſhe, I haue not ſo many:</l>
               <l>But if that I had as many mo</l>
               <l>as I haue, and halfe as many thereto,</l>
               <l>And ouer that halfe, halfe as many,</l>
               <l>and two Geeſe &amp; a half, then had I twenty.</l>
               <l>How many Géeſe had ſhe now truely?</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="proverbs">
            <pb facs="tcp:15563:20"/>
            <head>Choice and wittie Prouerbs.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> SO great is the ill that doth not hurt mee, as is the good that doth not help mee.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> Hee that for the new, leaueth the olde way, oftentimes is found to goe aſtray.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> Giuen is dead: and reſtored is nought.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Conceale not the truth from the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician and Laywer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> A young Barber and an olde Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> To looke for and not to come: To bee in bed, and not aſléepe: To ſerue and not to be accepted, are thrée tedious things.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> He that will not indure labour in this world, let him not be borne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> There is no vertue that pouertie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth not.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> The abundance of things ingendreth diſdainefulneſſe.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:21"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> He that ſitteth well, thinketh ill.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> The mirth of the world dureth but a while.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> He that vſeth mee better then hee is wont, hath betrayed me, or will betray me.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> He that doth not that whith he ought, that haps to him which he neuer thought.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> He that hath time, hath life.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> Al weapons of war cannot arme fear.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> He helpes little, that helpes not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> So much is mine, as I poſſeſſe; and, giue or loſe for for Gods ſake.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> Chuſe not a woman, nor linnen cloth by the candle.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> Kinſman helpes kinſman: but woe be to him that hath nothing.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20</hi> Honours alter Manners.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21</hi> Hee knoweth enough that knoweth nought, if hee knoweth how to holde his peace.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22</hi> A man aſſaulted is halfe taken.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23</hi> Hee that is wiſe in his owne eyes, there is more hope of a foole than ſuch a one.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24</hi> Old ſinne, new repentance.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25</hi> Sin that is hidden, is halfe forgiuen.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26</hi> An ounce of ſtate, requires a pound of gold.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:21"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>27</hi> He that liues well, dies well.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28</hi> Hee that iudures hir; ouercommeth her.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29</hi> Fly that preſent pleaſure, which paines thee after wards.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30</hi> Euery extreamitie is a fault.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31</hi> Euery queſtion requireth not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32</hi> Patience is ſorrowes remedy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>33</hi> Conſcience ſerues for a thouſand wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>34</hi> Nature is the true law.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>35</hi> All feare is bondage.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>36</hi> Things preſent are iudged by things paſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>37</hi> That is well done, which is done ſoone inough.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>38</hi> There is a remedy for all dolors, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>39</hi> The Law groweth of ſinne, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſeth it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>40</hi> The like I ſay, ſits with the Iay.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>41</hi> Birds of a feather flée together.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>42</hi> One man is worth a hundred, and a hundred are not worth one.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>43</hi> A wiſe man ought not to be aſhamed to change his purpoſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>44</hi> Maruell is the daughter of Ignorance.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:22"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>45</hi> The deeds are manly, and the words womanly.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>46</hi> The more that riches is honoured, ſhe more is vertue deſpiſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>47</hi> Time is the father of Truth, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience is the mother of Science.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>48</hi> Hee that ſoweth vertue, reapeth ſame.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>49</hi> Betimes in the Fiſhambles, and late in the Butchery.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>50</hi> To a good vnderſtander, halfe a word is enough.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>51</hi> Flies goe to leane horſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>52</hi> Hee that hath the world at will ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth wife.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>53</hi> Prouide a Figge for thy friend; and a Peach for thy enemy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>54</hi> The harts mirth, makes the face faire.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>55</hi> At mariages and burials, friends and kinſfolkes be knowne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>56</hi> A dradly diſeaſe neither Phyſician nor phyſicke can eaſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>57</hi> The loue of a harlot, and wine of a fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, is good in the morning, and naught in the euening.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>58</hi> An Aſſe pricked muſt needs trot.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>59</hi> Hee daunceth well enough, to whom fortune pipeth.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:22"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>60</hi> Hee gaineth enough, whom fortune loſeth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>61</hi> A dead Bée maketh no hony.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>62</hi> By one, and one, the ſpindles are made vp.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>63</hi> Faire words, and wicked déedes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ine wiſe men and fooles.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>64</hi> Ill goes the Boat without Oares.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>65</hi> An old band, is a Captaines honour.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>66</hi> A Barking dog ſildome bites.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>67</hi> An old dog barkes not in vaine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>68</hi> A running horſe; an open graue.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>69</hi> A faire ſhop and little gaine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>70</hi> He that buyeth deere, and taketh vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on credit, ſhall euer ſell to his loſſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>71</hi> A fire of ſtraw yéeldes naught but ſmoake.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>72</hi> Hee that hunts two Hares, loſeth both.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>73</hi> Hee that is in pouertie, is in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>74</hi> Hee that hath a good Speare, let him trie him.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>75</hi> Hee that doeth nothing, doeth euer amiſſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>76</hi> Hee that doth amiſſe, may doe well.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>77</hi> He that doth ill hateth the light.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>78</hi> He that hath no heart, hath legges.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:23"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>79</hi> He that hath no wiſe beateth her often</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>80</hi> He that hath no children, doth bring them vp well.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>81</hi> Hee that hath not ſerued, knoweth not how to command.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>82</hi> He that cannot beate the horſe, beate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the ſaddle.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>83</hi> He that doth not robbe, makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> roabe or a gowne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>84</hi> He that hurts another, hurts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>85</hi> A common ſeruant, is no mans ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>86</hi> Hee that ſerues harlots, a is ſlaue to ſinne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>87</hi> He that will haue all, loſethall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>88</hi> He that goes to bed with dogs, ariſe with fleas.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>89</hi> He that goes to bed without his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is out of quiet all night.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>90</hi> Hee that goes and comes makes a good voyage.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>91</hi> Hee that liues in Court, dies vpon ſtraw.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>92</hi> Speake no ill of another, till thou thinkeſt of thy ſelfe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>93</hi> One crow neuer puls out anothers eyes.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:23"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>94</hi> From word to deed is a great ſpce.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>95</hi> Folly is wiſe in her owne eyes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>96</hi> Hard with hard neuer made good wall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>97</hi> Faire ſpeech ſubdueth anger.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>98</hi> It is a goodly thing to take two Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons with one Beane.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>99</hi> Faire gayning, makes faire ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>g.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>100</hi> Miſchiefe comes by pounds, and goes away by ounces.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>101</hi> Marriners craft is the groſſeſt, yet of handy crafts the ſubtilleſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>102</hi> He whoſe belly is full, bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eues not him that is faſting.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>103</hi> The Peach will haue wine, the Fig water.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>104</hi> Fiſh marreth the water, and fleſh amends it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>105</hi> He promiſes mountaines, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes mole-hils.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>106</hi> Promiſing is the vigil of giuing.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>107</hi> More then enough breakes the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>108</hi> Sparing is the firſt gaining.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>109</hi> Wine by the ſauour, bread by the colour.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>110</hi> Experience is ſomtimes dangerous.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15563:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>111</hi> Make mee a diuinour, and I will make thee rich.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>112</hi> Friars obſeruants ſpare their one, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d eate other mens.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>113</hi> A gloued cat can catch no mice.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>114</hi> A broken bagge can hold no meal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>115</hi> It thou wilt come with me, br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> with thee.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>116</hi> Offices may well be giuen, br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> diſcretion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>117</hi> Suffer the ill, and looke for the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>118</hi> In the world their bee men that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> haue the egge, and the hen.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>119</hi> Aboue God there is no Lord.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>120</hi> Aboue blacke there is no colour, and aboue ſalt their is no fauour.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>121</hi> If it were not for hope the heart would breake.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>122</hi> Cut off a dogs taile, hee will bee a dogge ſtill.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>123</hi> Naught is that Muſe that findes no excuſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>124</hi> Nought are thoſe houſes where the Hen crowes, and the Cock holds his peace.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>125</hi> He is in ill caſe that giues example to another.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>126</hi> Too much hope deceiueth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>127</hi> All draw water to their own mill. <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:15563:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15563:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
